All right. בוקר טוב. Boker Tov. Today's דף daf is ס"ז, Samech
Zayin, 67. We pick up at the very bottom of ס"ו עמוד
ב', Samech Vav Amud Bet, a little bit before the משנה. Mishnah.
We are dealing with the previous משנה, Mishnah, sending off the שעיר,
Sa'ir, the
goat. We had a whole discussion about what happens if they get
sick, that you can do it on שבת, Shabbat, ride it on
the shoulders. Fascinating digression about רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and giving sort
of indirect answers to things, refusing to answer a question of a
woman. And now we pick up from four lines down in the
wide lines. כבש עשו לו, Kevesh asu lo, they made a ramp
for the guy who was going to take out the goat. אמר
רבה בר בר חנה, Amar Rabba Bar Bar Chana, לא בבליים היו,
lo Bavli'im hayu, when it says that
the בבליים Bavli'im who would basically attack the guy and pull his
hair and say, "Get out of here, take our sins away." So
רבה בר בר חנה Rabba Bar Bar Chana said, לא בבליים היו,
lo Bavli'im hayu, they weren't really בבליים, Bavli'im, אלא אלכסנדרים היו, ella
Alexandrim hayu, they were Alexandrian Jews, which tends to be pretty assimilated
Jews, but interesting, maybe they came up for the special יום כיפור
Yom Kippur service. Right.
ומתוך ששונאים את הבבליים,
Umitoch she-shon'im et
ha-Bavli'im,
but because the, not presumably the Alexandrian Jews, presumably the רבנים, rabbanim,
or the כהנים, Kohanim, whatever, we assume the רבנים, rabbanim, the authors
of the משנה, Mishnah, hated the בבליים. Bavli'im. It doesn't tell us
that. היו קורין אותן על שמן. Hayu korin otan al sheman. They
would call, you know, any people that they didn't like, maybe particularly
people that they thought were acting barbaric. Although it's quite ironic because,
you know, Alexandrians were very assimilated and therefore they were probably the
most cultured, acculturated but cultured, you know. So I'm not exactly sure
what type of associations they had with the idea of בבליים. Bavli'im.
Even when you call somebody a name, normally it's because the name
carries with it certain specific types of associations, not just we don't
like them. So you do wonder what type of associations,
you know,
the people in ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, the תנאים Tannaim would have
associated with בבליים Bavli'im that they thought was appropriate to associate with
the Alexandrians. Anyway, they called them בבליים. Bavli'im. Okay. Maybe a little
bit of warfare between תלמוד בבלי Talmud Bavli and ירושלמי? Yerushalmi?
Yeah,
maybe.
It's interesting, you know, you wonder whether it means בבליים Bavli'im doesn't
literally mean like the אמוראים Amoraim that were in בבל? Bavel? Does
it mean the common people? You know, and you do get these
comments, right,
הני בבליאי טפשאי, hanei Bavli'ei tipshai, we just had recently, stupid Babylonians,
they dwell in a dark land and they eat dark bread, maybe.
Although בבל Bavel is not the same as Diaspora, Diaspora was מדינת
הים, Medinat Hayam, you know. But some sense, look, it could have
been ironic also. It could have been that these Alexandrians think that
they're so refined and so cultured, you know, and you're דווקא davka
attaching a name that maybe would be associated with the, with the
most ignorant, like uncultured. I don't really know. Anyway, they called them
בבליים. Bavli'im. Okay. תניא ותנו בריתא, Tanya ve-tanu b'raita, רבי יהודה אומר
לא בבליים היו אלא אלכסנדרים היו. Rabbi Yehuda omer lo Bavli'im hayu
ella Alexandrim hayu. They weren't בבליים, Bavli'im, they were Alexandrians. אמר לו
רבי יוסי, Amar lo Rabbi Yosi, so רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi said
to him, תנוח דעתך שהנחת דעתי. Tanuach da'atacha she-inachta et da'ati. Your,
you know, your, your mind should be set at ease because you
set my mind at ease. And רש"י Rashi says it's because he
himself was descendant from בבליים. Bavli'im. And תוספות Tosafot points out that
there's another גמרא Gemara that says exact the reverse, that רבי יוסי
Rabbi Yosi says that certain people were not בבליים, Bavli'im, they were
Alexandrians, and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda said to him, "Your mind should
be set at ease, you set my mind at ease." So there's
a little question about that. Of course, the funny thing is, is
that okay, fine, so we say that these people, these particular offenders
on יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, not offenders, but people doing this offensive
things, were not בבליים. Bavli'im. But on the other hand, we are
saying that you use בבליים Bavli'im as a pejorative. So it's making
more of a general statement about בבליים Bavli'im and negative associations with
them. Okay, ומה היו אומרים לו, U-mah hayu omerim lo, so they
said to him, "Take the sins, get out and go." תנא ותנו
בריתא, Tana ve-tanu b'raita, מה שהיתא צפירא דין, Ma shahita tzapira dein,
why are you letting or leaving like postponing,
tarrying with this goat, וחוביי דרא סגיאין, ve-chovei dara sagi'in, and the
sins of the generation are so great? Get this goat out of
here, get all the, get all our sins out of here. Okay,
so it's interesting, what?
צפירא Tzapira is a goat? Is a שעיר, Sa'ir, yeah. Okay. So
it's interesting, it has it in Aramaic, presumably actually some form of
a direct quote.
Makes them sound like בבליים Bavli'im really.
Well, ha, because good point, because they're speaking Aramaic, if they were
Alexandrians they would be speaking Greek. That's a very good point. Maybe
that's a קשיא kashya on the previous approach. All right, next משנה.
Mishnah.
Question, is there a ירושלמי Yerushalmi about this?
About this בבליים Bavli'im and whatever? I haven't checked. There is a
ירושלמי Yerushalmi on יומא. Yoma. I haven't checked what they say on
this משנה. Mishnah.
Okay.
מיקירי ירושלים, Meyakkirei Yerushalayim, מיקירי ירושלים, Meyakkirei Yerushalayim, from the honored people
of ירושלים, Yerushalayim, היו מלוין אותו עד סוכה הראשונה. hayu melavin oto
ad sukkah harishonah.
So although they said that in theory anybody could go with the
goat, they made a practice to only use כהנים. Kohanim. Nevertheless, they
had, they made a practice. Okay, so he would be an honor
position was that the important people of ירושלים Yerushalayim would accompany the
guy with the goat. Okay, so they would not be the guy
themselves, but they'd accompany him. And they would accompany him until the
first סוכה, sukah, until the first hut. עשר סוכות מירושלים ועד צוק.
Eser sukkos miYerushalayim ve'ad tzuk.
There were ten huts. This is not סוכות Sukkos is just five
days away, but this is not meant in the ritual sense. There
were ten huts from ירושלים Yerushalayim until the cliff. תשעים ריס, Tish'im
ris,
90 ריס, ris, which is some measure, would be from ירושלים Yerushalayim
to the cliff. We'll say that in a minute. שבעה ומחצה לכל
מיל, Shiva u'mechetza lechol mil,
seven and a half ריס ris per מיל. mil. A מיל mil
is 2000 אמות. amos. It's תחום שבת. techum Shabbos. It is roughly
a kilometer. It's interesting why here it uses the 90 ריס ris
since it's always comfortable to use the מיל. mil. Basically there were
12 מיל, mil, 12 kilometers until the cliff. So 12 kilometers is
about what? It's about seven miles, something like that. Seven miles until
the cliff. Okay, so somebody can go get out a map and
look what is there seven miles from
הר הבית, Har Habayis, what was the most likely cliff? But they
presumably use the same place all the time, right? Yeah, presumably they
use the same place.
Now if there were 10 סוכות, sukkos,
okay, if there were 10 סוכות, sukkos,
right,
so here is your הר הבית. Har Habayis.
Okay, you get one, two, three, now whatever, four, five, six, seven,
we'll go that way, okay, right, eight, nine, 10. Okay, if there's
12 מיל, mil, right, we just said 90 ריס ris is 12
מיל. mil. Okay, so there's a מיל mil per each, one מיל,
mil, one
kilometer per each סוכה, sukah, there's your little סוכה. sukah. Okay, one
kilometer to get each סוכה, sukah, so you'd be at 10 kilometers
and then from here to the cliff is two מיל mil from
the last one to get off and then you're and then you're
at the cliff. Okay, and here's the goat. So basically you'd go
12 kilometers, 12 מיל, mil, right? And between each at every at
every what מיל mil there would be a there would be a
סוכה. sukah. Now a מיל, mil, if you remember, 2000 אמות amos
is תחום שבת, techum Shabbos, okay, how far you can walk outside
the city limits. So the people that would accompany him would go,
right, the people from ירושלים Yerushalayim would accompany him to the first
סוכה. sukah. They would go with him to and then they'd stop,
right? So they would go to their תחום שבת. techum Shabbos. Then
you'd get another guy to accompany him, right, to the second.
So he was being led all over יום כיפור.
Yom Kippur. He would go the whole 12, but there would be
people at each סוכה sukah to accompany him for the next 2000
אמות. amos. Each one of them would not go out of their
תחום שבת. techum Shabbos. He would obviously be given license to do
what he needed to do. They would be limited to their תחום
שבת, techum Shabbos, so he would have people accompany him until the
very end. Until here, the guy, the last guy that accompanied him
would not go all the way with him to the cliff, would
stand here, right, would stand here at the end of one מיל
mil and he would go he would go with the goat the
final מיל mil by himself. But he'd just, also how did he
get, how
yeah
did he have like a leash? It doesn't sound like you never
hear that he had like a leash, but he's not gonna follow?
That's a good point. I don't know if the goat walk with
people? If you go like if you go jogging with your dogs,
their dogs jog alongside them, right?
Not every dog it's not a,
so
maybe he had a leash. Maybe, but you know it's interesting, if
he had a leash, then when it was discussing the whole issue
about carrying they would have mentioned the leash. So it doesn't sound
like it.
It doesn't sound like he has a what do you call it,
a collar, I don't know.
What did he do on each סוכה, sukah, did
he eat each, he doesn't do anything. יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. Yes,
good question. So all the people in each one of these סוכות
sukkos which is along the way, that
means they're staying there all day.
Yeah, they stay there.
Yeah. Okay, so they stay there, those people, okay, those people stayed
there for the whole, so those people stayed in the סוכות, sukkos,
Michael just asked, those people stayed in the סוכות sukkos the entire
יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. So by the way, it doesn't say that
the honored people of ירושלים Yerushalayim were at every סוכה. sukah. The
honored people of ירושלים Yerushalayim went to the first סוכה sukah and
then went back home. If you're a חשוב chashuv person, you're going
back home for the rest of יום כיפור Yom Kippur and you're
going to be in the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash or wherever you're
going to be. But other people got the job of being in
the סוכה sukah for the entire יום כיפור Yom Kippur and just
being able to be there to walk him for that part of
the journey. Okay, so let's take a look. So it says like
this:
על כל סוכה וסוכה, Al kol sukah ve'sukah, by every סוכה sukah
that he would pass, אומרים לו, omrim lo, they would say to
him, הרי מזון והרי מים. harei mazon v'harei mayim. Look, if you're
tired, if you're weary, there's water, there's food, you can go ahead
and have it.
Okay. Anyway, ומלווים אותו מסוכה לסוכה, u'mhalvim oto misukkah l'sukkah, they would
accompany him from one סוכה sukkah to the next, as I described,
חוץ, chutz, with the exception of מאחרון שבהן, me'aharon shebahen,
the last one would not go the whole two מיל, mil, because
that would be anyway outside of תחום שבת, tchum Shabbat, he would
go one מיל mil and then he'd stand a מיל mil away
and the guy did the last מיל mil by himself to go
to the צוק. tzuk. אלא עומד מרחוק ורואה את מעשיו, ela omed
merachok v'roeh et ma'asav,
he'd stand at a distance, the last guy who'd accompany him, and
see what he was doing. ומה היה עושה, u'mah haya oseh, what
would he do when he got to the צוק? tzuk? חולק לשון
של זהורית, cholek lashon shel zehorit,
he would divide the red string, חציו קשר בסלע, chetzyo kashar basela,
half of it he would tie on a rock nearby, וחציו קשר
בין שני קרניו, v'chetzyo kashar bein shnei karnav,
and the other half he would tie between the two horns of
the goat. Yeah, I don't know, maybe it was a קשר, kesher,
maybe it was a maybe it was a loop knot or קשר
של קיימא. kesher shel kayama. Basically, there seems that he, he had
at last to do whatever he needed to do. Now of course,
it's one thing to say you needed to do the actual עבודה.
avodah. This whole red string is only is is nowhere in the
פסוקים psukim that it says this, you know, presumably it's all rabbinic,
so it is interesting, it's exactly correct, like were we allowed certain
מלאכות, melachot, you know, in order for him to do the red
string? I mean, look, he can tie a knot without it being
a permanent knot, without it being an without it being
an expert knot.
Yeah, it's true, you could cut, but again, if you don't cut
in exact, but cutting the fabric, that's true, you're cutting the fabric,
well a string isn't fabric, is it קורע koreiah or מחתוך? mechathech?
Might be there's just מחתוך, mechathech, it's not really a fabric, it's
a string. Anyway, food and water. What? Well there's the food and
water, but that at least we'll discuss whether he would actually partake
of it, but that at least was necessary for him to do
the job as opposed to the string that was only something added
on later that wasn't an actual part of the עבודה. avodah.
It could be Jewish, didn't they say it could be a זר
zar somewhere?
No, we we said it can be a non-כהן, Kohen, we did
not say non-Jew.
Okay, okay, it's a long walk in the מדבר midbar on a
very hot day without eating food.
All right. But and drinking. Right, right, right.
It'll take several hours.
Right.
Okay, well depends how fast you run or whatever, but right. I
mean, seven miles on a walking would be about what, like three
hours, two and a half hours?
Okay, ודחפו לאחוריו, udchafu leachorav, and he would push it backwards. It's
not exactly clear, presumably the goat's backwards, not him, so he pushed
the goat off of the צוק, tzuk, the goat would be go
falling backwards off the צוק, tzuk, which somehow seems even like more
dras, you know, I don't know, dramatic or something. Maybe you couldn't
push the goat forward, the goat sees what's happening, so you have
to push the goat backwards.
This is semantics though, say it's very yeah,
they were I
yeah, I don't know if we why should we assume it's a
mountain goat, probably was a domesticated goat from somebody's flock.
Goats are
uh-huh.
Yeah, I don't know how he would manage to do it. והוא
מתגלגל ויורד, v'hu mitgalgel v'yored, and the goat would tumble down and
fall down the
צוק, tzuk, ולא היה מגיע לחצי ההר עד שנעשה אברים אברים, v'lo
haya magiya l'chatzi hahar ad she-na'aseh evarim evarim, and before it even
got halfway down the mountain, presumably it was a sheer cliff with
like a lot of outcroppings and rocks and and so on, so
before it even hit the bottom, it would shatter into into its
limbs. בא וישב לו תחת סוכה אחרונה, ba v'yashav lo tachat sukkah
acharonah,
so then this guy who pushed it off, the איש עתי, ish
iti, would come and sit in the last סוכה, sukkah, he'd walk
back two תחומין. tchumin. רש"י Rashi points out that even though normally
even when we give somebody license to leave תחום שבת, tchum Shabbat,
like for the sake of a פיקוח נפש pikuach nefesh or a
midwife, once, you know, once they're done with their job, we don't
let them, you know, we limit them to 2,000 אמות. amot. This
guy is going back, you know, 4,000 אמות, amot, but nevertheless, you
know, we made special concessions. Yeah, why wouldn't we? Yeah, and רש"י
Rashi also says he's very tired, so I you know, he's obviously
weak and tired and and staying out in the מדבר midbar is
dangerous, dangerous because of the elements, dangerous because of who walks around
in the מדבר. midbar. So him we let go back. It's not
like he's in a city that he can stay there. Okay, עד
שתחשך, ad she-techshach, until it gets dark. ומאימתי מטמא בגדים, u'me'eimatai metamei
begadim,
when does during this process he it lead to the impurity of
the clothes? Because the תורה Torah says והמשלח את השעיר לעזאזל יכבס
בגדיו, v'hamishale'ach et hasa'ir la'azazel yechabes begadav, that the guy who does
it gets has to clean his clothes, meaning he becomes טמא. tamei.
So when is this? משיצא חוץ לחומת ירושלים, misheyatza chutz l'chomat Yerushalayim,
from the time he leaves the walls of ירושלים. Yerushalayim. רבי שמעון
אומר, Rabbi Shimon omer, משעת דחייתו לצוק, mishat dchiyato latzuk, only after
it gets pushed off. Now again, you might have wanted to connect
that to when is it considered like you're יוצא yotzei this עבודה,
avodah, but you might remember that the according to the גמרא, Gemara,
could be you're יוצא yotzei from the time you do the גורל,
goral, could be you're יוצא yotzei from the time you do the
וידוי, viduy, right? I mean, you know, it says that after the
וידוי, viduy, nothing it's not done with בגדי לבן, bigdei lavan, you
know, it's somebody else it's not the כהן, Kohen, it's somebody else
doing it. So presumably this isn't needed to be יוצא, yotzei, although
we do find out and we will find out and we'll see
in a minute in the גמרא. Gemara. that the whole string turning
white didn’t happen just because you did the וידוי, viduy, it happened
at the end of this process. So there could be a different
question in terms of what do I need in order to fulfill
the ritual obligations of doing the עבודה avoda in the בית המקדש
Beis Hamikdash on יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, did you do the עבודה
avoda check because I did the וידוי, viduy, but in terms of
the efficacy of effecting the כפרה kapara or at least doing it
in a fully way, maybe that requires the actual pushing off the
cliff? I think that’s an interesting thing to think about. Normally we
sort of assume that what halachically consists of doing what is required,
well if you’ve done what is required, then you’ve achieved the efficacy
of the
עבודה. avoda. Here I think it is interesting. The string doesn’t turn
white until it goes over the cliff, but we’ve said you probably
בדיעבד bediavad after the וידוי, viduy, maybe even if nothing happens it’s
okay, which is again very, very shocking for us. Is it possible
there’s a difference between when you’re יוצא yotzei and when actually it
achieves the כפרה? kapara? Okay, so just something to think about. Let's
take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. תנו רבנן, Tano rabanan, okay
we taught in a ברייתא. Braisa. עשר סוכות ושנים עשר מיל היו,
דברי רבי מאיר. Eser sukkot u-shneim asar milim hayu, divrei Rabbi Meir.
So that’s the assumption of our משנה. Mishnah. Ten סוכות sukkot and
twelve מיל. mil. רבי יהודה אומר תשע סוכות ועשרה מיל. Rabbi Yehuda
omer tesha sukkot va-asara milim. No, it was only ten מיל mil
and there were nine סוכות. sukkot. So according to him, he could
have been accompanied from the guy from the last סוכה sukka the
full way to the edge of the cliff, right? Understand, there are
nine points, then the last guy from point nine till the end
of the tenth מיל mil could accompany him the whole way. רבי
יוסי אומר. Rabbi Yosi omer. Right, our משנה Mishnah is
רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. רבי יוסי אומר חמש סוכות ועשרה מיל היו.
Rabbi Yosi omer chamesh sukkot va-asara milim hayu. Okay, there were five
סוכות sukkot and ten מיל. mil. Now how could that be? וכולן
על ידי עירוב. Vekulan al yedei eruv. And all of them were
by an עירוב. eruv. Because why is, since these guys are just
going in one direction, why are you limiting them to one מיל?
mil? If the guy is sitting in this סוכה, sukka, maybe he’s
spending the time in this סוכה sukka because it’s protected, but let
him make his עירוב eruv here. And if he makes his עירוב
eruv here, he has one מיל mil from the עירוב eruv and
one מיל mil in each direction from where he made the עירוב.
eruv. So every guy in the סוכה sukka makes his עירוב eruv
at the end of a מיל mil from the סוכה sukka and
can go two מיל. mil. So if you make your עירוב eruv
at a מיל mil away, you can go two מיל mil in
one
direction. Therefore he said you can do the whole thing with ten
מיל, mil, you can cover it with five סוכות sukkot because everybody's
just moving in one direction and then back to the סוכה. sukka.
Now here's the point: the guy
from the other one can go back with him.
We’re going to get to that in a minute, but that’s not
what
he says. Okay. That’s a good point too, but that's not what
he says. Because he says על ידי עירוב. al yedei eruv. According
to you, you don’t need an עירוב. eruv. All right, we’ll get
to that in a minute. But he’s saying that no, everybody goes
in one direction, but each guy can go two תחומים, techumim, four
thousand אמה, ama, two מיל. mil. אמר רבי יוסי, Amar Rabbi Yosi,
so רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi says once I came up with this
idea that you can use an עירוב eruv to extend the reach
per סוכה, sukka, סח לי אלעזר בני, Sachli Elazar beni, so אלעזר
Elazar my son said to me, סח לי Sachli spoke to me,
רש"י Rashi says almost like in a joking manner, אם על ידי
עירוב, im al yedei eruv, if you want to use an עירוב
eruv to sort of extend the reach, יכול אני לעשות אפילו שתי
סוכות ועשרה מיל. yakhol ani la'asot afilu shtei sukkot va-asara milim.
I can get you to cover ten מיל mil with two סוכות.
sukkot. How do you do it? Because what you do is you
have as Michael said, people going in both directions. Not only are
people going in both directions, just get two people in a סוכה.
sukka. So if here’s סוכה sukka number one, here’s סוכה sukka number
two. Okay, here’s this guy, right? So this person here can go,
and there are two people in each סוכה. sukka. Guy number one
and guy number two. Guy number one makes an עירוב eruv over
here. So he can go two מיל mil this way and start
with the guy with the goat and he can get the first
two מיל. mil. This guy can go this way to meet him
and then come back. This guy can go, make his עירוב eruv
here and goes two מיל mil that way. Stay with me? Then
the guy here in B, you have also two guys, this guy
makes his עירוב eruv here and gets to go two מיל mil
that way and meets him midway. That gets you another two מיל.
mil. And then this guy makes his עירוב eruv here and gets
to go two מיל. mil. So that’s two, four, six, eight. How
do we get ten? The last step is just by his own,
hold on. Let’s think. How did you get ten? Minute. שני מילים,
shnei milim, יצאו מקצת מבית מן ארבע. yatzu miketzas mibeis min arba.
סוכה שנייה לסוף ארבע, Sukka shniya lesof arba, סוכה ראשונה לסוף ירושלים
sukka rishona lesof Yerushalayim so they are getting him. getting him to
two מילין, milin, right? Out of the city. Oh, yeah, you're right.
Side, side. Right. The people that accompanied him, right, here's ירושלים, Yerushalayim,
thank you, Michael, here's ירושלים, Yerushalayim, so the people in ירושלים Yerushalayim
made an עירוב eiruv here. Right, so they get to two מילין
milin that way, thank you. And then these guys made an עירוב
eiruv halfway. If so, you could do the whole thing with two
סוכות, sukkos, if you have two people per סוכה sukkah and everybody
is making עירובים eiruvim in opposite directions. Okay, but that's not actually
what happened. He's just saying, hey, we didn't make עירובים. eiruvim. If
so, we wouldn't be talking about this. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara
says like this: כמאן אזלא, Keman azla, who's it going like? חוץ
מאחרון שבהן שלא הגיע עמו לצוק. Chutz mei-achron she-bahen she-lo higia imo
la-tzuk. So it's funny why it quotes the ברייתא, Baraisa, our משנה
Mishna says it, but anyway, who's it going like, the idea that
he would not be accompanied all the way up to the cliff?
אלא עומד מרחוק ורואה מעשיו, Ella omeid me-rachok ve-roeh ma'asav, he stands
at a distance. כמאן? Keman? כרבי מאיר, Ke-Rebbi Meir, that's like רבי
מאיר Rebbi Meir because according to רבי יהודה, Rebbi Yehuda, it would
be nine סוכות sukkos and ten מילין, milin, he could be accompanied
over to the edge. According to רבי יוסי, Rebbi Yosi, five סוכות
sukkos but with an עירוב, eiruv, he could be accompanied up to
the edge of ten. It's only according to רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda
that there's ten סוכות sukkos and twelve מילין milin that he was
not accompanied to the very edge. Okay. על כל סוכה וסוכה אומרים
לו הרי מזון והרי מים. Al kol sukkah ve-sukkah omerim lo harey
mazon ve-harey mayim. At every סוכה sukkah they would say to him,
there is, you know, there's water and food. So תניא, tanya, we
taught in a ברייתא, Baraisa, מעולם לא הוצרך אדם לכך, Me-olam lo
hutzrach adam le-kach, nobody ever actually needed to get the water and
the food. אלא, Ella, so why did they do it? שאינו דומה
מי שיש לו פת בסלו למי שאין לו פת בסלו, She-eino domeh
mi she-yesh lo pas be-salo le-mi she-ein lo pas be-salo, famous phrase
in the גמרא, Gemara, usually it means metaphorically, here it's almost literal.
It's not similar somebody who has bread in his basket, somebody who
doesn't have bread in his basket. The fact that you know it's
available and ready for you means that you're less desirous. No, no,
it's okay, I can do without. But all of a sudden somebody
tells you it's not available or you're not allowed to have it,
and then all of a sudden it's the only thing you can
focus on is where's, why can't I get some bread and water?
I'm starving, I'm thirsty. Where's that phrase more famously פת בסלו? pas
be-salo? The גמרא Gemara uses it in a sexual context about, for
example, why a husband and wife can sleep together in the same
room even when the wife is a נידה, niddah, even when the
wife is a נידה, niddah, why aren't we afraid that they'll sin?
Because, you know, they can be having sex at a later time,
you know, it's just now they can't, so it's פת בסלו pas
be-salo and so on. The גמרא Gemara had it before about the
rabbis that would go to a town and announce who wants to
be my wife for the day? You know, the פת בסלו, pas
be-salo, so it does use that. Look, we have in the תורה
Torah bread being used as a metaphor for sex, right? כי אם
הלחם אשר הוא אוכל, Ki im ha-lechem asher hu ochel, by יוסף
Yosef and so on. Now the interesting thing here is, was he
actually allowed to eat and drink for doing it? Because on the
one thing we sort of say המועד אפילו בשבת אפילו בטומאה אפילו
ביום כיפור, ha-moed afilu be-Shabbos afilu be-tumah afilu be-Yom Kippur, you can
violate, you know, שבת Shabbos and יום כיפור Yom Kippur to do
it, but is it just the מלאכה melacha that you can violate
of יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, it overrides the מלאכה melacha prohibitions, or
would it even override the eating prohibitions of יום כיפור Yom Kippur
and to what degree are those seen as of one piece? So
there actually is some debate in the ראשונים Rishonim about whether he
actually would be allowed. The גמרא Gemara never says one way or
the other, but it would be funny to think it would be
פת בסלו pas be-salo if it if we're telling you you can
do it but if you really had to do it we would
tell you you couldn't. You'd think at some stage somebody might catch
on to that. Okay, but anyway, but that is not made explicit
in the גמרא Gemara whether it actually would be allowed. Okay, so
let's take a look. One minute. I mean it wouldn't be like
הותרה yutrah form, right? Only like דחויה, dechuya, so to speak, of
eating יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. Like you felt like, alright, I'll have...
Okay, so for example, here's what the תוספות ישנים Tosafos Yeshanim says,
if you want to see that, it's the bottom of ס''ח ע''א,
Samech-Ches amud Aleph, two lines from the bottom or three lines, again
in these microscopic lines, but here's what he says. He says לא
הוצרך אדם לכך, Lo hutzrach adam le-kach, he says אבל אם היה
צריך, Aval im hayah tzarich, if he would have needed the food,
היו מאכילים אותו, hayu ma'achilim oso, they would have given it to
him. ואפילו היה יוצר דוחק שעיר, Ve-afilu hayah yotzer dochek sa'eer, so
it's a little unclear what the גירסא girsa is, but יוצר דוחק
שעיר, yotzer dochek sa'eer, even if it would not have been like,
you know, pushed, if it would... I mean I think he's saying
אפילו היה יוצר דוחק שעיר, afilu hayah yotzer dochek sa'eer, it's not
that big of a deal. Yeah, it might mean that even if
by not doing it it wouldn't prevent him from pushing off the
שעיר, sa'eer, it's a little unclear what that means. But here he
goes on וכבאינו כמו שבת וטומאה, u-ke-vainu kemo Shabbos ve-tumah, the same
way it overrides שבת Shabbos and טומאה, tumah, presumably you remember you
override טומאה tumah to use the guy you appointed even though you
could use another guy. So I think part of the question is,
hey, why don't we just avoid the food problem and go to
a closest cliff, right? Why do we allow ourselves to go so
far away a cliff? Well, once something overrides, you know, it overrides
even if it's like הותרה, yutrah, even if there, you know, to
do it in the ideal way. Anyway, wasn't there a closest cliff?
Maybe anyway it... And we're talking here that if he was, if
we have a fetus, it would be because of danger, life threatening,
right? כגון שאחזו בולמוס k'gon she'achazo bulmus like he has like this
starvation, you know, disease took hold of him and if he didn't
eat he would die. וזו שאמרו יודע שעם ירעב ביותר ויאחזנו בולמוס
יתנו לו לאכול ve'zu she'amru yode'a she'im yera'av beyoter ve'yo'achzenu bulmus yitnu
lo le'echol and because he knew that had he gotten to be
a point of being in a סכנה sakana they would let him
eat, so then לא היה רעב כל כך lo haya ra'ev kol
kach he wouldn't be so hungry. So there really seems to be
almost two contradictory answers. The first answer is it's like שבת Shabbat
and טומאה tumah it overrides, doesn't matter if it was absolutely necessary,
not absolutely necessary, you know, if you want to feed it, this
thing overrides. The other answer seems to be, no, no, no, it
only would have overridden had he gotten himself to the point of
being in a סכנה. sakana. Then it would have overridden because he's
in a סכנה. sakana. It wouldn't have overridden for the sake of
the עבודה, avodah, it would have overridden because he got himself into
a סכנה. sakana. So although it sort of reads, you can tell
the text is not so good there, you like there's a little
problem with it, it reads like one answer, it seems like those
are two different answers, to what degree really we would have allowed
somebody to eat for the sake of doing this עבודה. avodah. Is
it really though? If he just wanted to eat, if he didn't
really need to? It seems to have two answers. One answer is
yes, even if he wanted to, like טומאה, tumah, and the other
answer seems to be no, only if he got to a point
of סכנה. sakana. But why the word בולמוס bulmus must be related
to the word bulimia? Yeah, yeah, it comes up in different, it
must be like dehydration. Yeah, comes up in a different גמרא. Gemara.
Okay. So back to our גמרא, Gemara, ס"ז עמוד א'. samech zayin
amud aleph. Okay. So, ומהו עושה חולק לשון של זהורית umahu oseh
cholek lashon shel zehorit he would take the red string. ונקשר חציו
בסלע venakshar chetzyo basela why do you split the string, tie it
all to a rock? כיון דמצוה בשעיר keivan demitzvah basair since the,
you know, he has to take care of pushing the goat off
the cliff, there's still a מצוה mitzvah to be done here, even
if it's not מעכב. me'akev. דילמא קדים ומלבין dilma kadim umalbin maybe
the string while he's bothering tying it to a rock would turn
white. Interesting, it turns white before he's gotten the goat off the
cliff. So when exactly was that moment that he effected the כפרה
kaparah is unclear. ומייתבא דעתיה umaitva dateih and he'll be oh good,
we're done and he'll walk home, he won't bother pushing the goat
off the cliff. He'll be settled, right? So the גמרא Gemara says
okay, ונקשר חציו בין קרניו venakshar chetzyo bein karnav do it all
between the horns because the assumption is that if you're tying it
on the
horns, even if you see it become white, you know, you're involved
with the goat, you're going to finish what you're doing.
Or רש"י Rashi says maybe because you're in the middle of doing
something with the goat, it wouldn't turn white yet.
Meaning then you wouldn't be finished the עבודה avodah what you're in
the middle of. Again, it's pretty
funny what moment
exactly it would turn white is very unclear. Anyway, but if you're
doing it on the goat, maybe that avoids the problem of forgetting
about pushing the goat over.
No, זימנין דגמיש ליה לרישיה zimnin degamish leih lerisheih
sometimes the goat will
bend over its head as it's rolling down and its head will
be tucked under its body. ולאו אדעתיה velav adateih and you won't
be able to, you know, right, ולאו אדעתיה velav adateih often means
like you won't notice it, but here it means you won't be
able to, you know, accidentally you won't notice it, but here it
means you won't be able to notice it
and obviously the whole point is we want to be able to
see the symbolism. I do want to point out by the way
in modern Hebrew the word גמיש gamish means flexible. So it's interesting
in terms of modern Hebrew. Yeah, but didn't they also tie the,
at the פתח בית המקדש petach Beit HaMikdash someplace? Let's take a
look. You know what? Perfect transition to the next point. תנו רבנן
tanu rabanan we taught: בראשונה היו קושרים לשון של זהורית על פתח
אולם מבחוץ. barishonah hayu koshrim lashon shel zehorit al petach ulam mibachutz.
It used to be like Michael said, they would put the red
string on the, they wouldn't have it on the goat at all.
They'd have, you know, because everybody else wants to know the symbolism.
What do we care about this one guy? Everybody else is in
the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. They put it by the doorway of
the אולם, Ulam, right, the hall leading into the היכל. Heichal. מבחוץ
mibachutz on the outside of the doorway. הלבין hilbin it would turn
red, היו שמחים hayu smeychim everybody would be happy. לא הלבין lo
hilbin it didn't turn red, היו עצבים hayu atzeivim everybody would be
dis, would be sad. I'm sorry, did I say white? It turned
white, thank you. Did I say that wrong before as well? Okay.
Go back and correct what I said before. Okay. It's about turning
white, it starts red. Fine. So anyway, so if it would turn
white, היו שמחים hayu smeychim everybody would be happy. לא הלבין lo
hilbin it didn't turn white, היו עצבים hayu atzeivim everybody would be
sad ומתביישים umitbayshim not only would they be sad, they'd be embarrassed,
like a public statement that they're not forgiven. They'd be ashamed. Thank
you. התקינו hitkinu they established היו קושרים על פתח אולם מבפנים. hayu
koshrim al petach ulam mibifnim. They would do it on the inside
of the door so, you know, maybe the כהנים kohanim would see,
some people would see, but it wouldn't get out to the people,
you know. ועדיין היו מציצים ורואים ve'adayin hayu metzitzim vero'im they would
still peek through and see it. Yeah, so, you know, again you
wonder as the door was, was it open, was it closed, you
know. I mean presumably it was open, right? Says we said before
that you know in order to שחט shachat the שלמים, shlamim, you
need a פתח אהל מועד, petach ohel mo'ed, you need the door
to be open, presumably they stayed open. So exactly where was it
put that it was hard to see but you could peek and
you could see it, I don't know. But anyway, would turn color
theoretically when he pushed it off. Maybe if they weren't getting a
כפרה kapparah that year, it wouldn't, and that's why they said it
could be it didn't turn color at all. Or maybe it did
turn white right away. Right, I have no idea. Okay. Okay, so
they... ודאי היו מציצים ורואים, vadai hayu metzitzim veroyim, they would peek
through and see it. היו שמחים hayu smeichim if it would be
turned white they'd be rejoiced. היו עצבים hayu atzevim if not they'd
be sad. התקינו, hitkinu, notice by the way this time it didn't
say they would be ashamed because it wouldn't be as public, okay,
so maybe they could be sad without being ashamed. התקינו שיהו קושרים
אותו, hitkinu sheyehu koshrim oto, so then they started saying forget doing
it in public, you know, where people can see. Tie it on
the goat, חציו בסלע וחציו בין קרניו, chetzyo basela vechetzyo bein karnav,
half on the rock, half on the on the horn. Here, the
guy'll come back maybe and he'll tell the people. So it's again
quite fascinating. This assumption that you had this, you have to have
this red string, it's nowhere in the תורה, Torah, obviously it's based
on the פסוק pasuk אם יהיו חטאיכם כשנים כשלג ילבינו, im yihyu
chataeichem kashanim kasheleg yalbinu, but that's, you know, a metaphor. The assumption
that they would do it and they had to find the right
place to do it, but it's taken for granted that you're going
to do something with this string. Look, it's a miracle, clearly you're
doing the right thing, but what gave them the idea to start
with it? Anyway, once you're doing it on the goat, what's the
point that this one guy knows? So maybe he'll come back and
he'll report. You know, maybe the guy... I know, I don't know
what to say about that, it's quite funny. Okay. Goat is tied
to the rock? No, the rock is nearby, just a place to
put down the string so some string is tied to the goat
and some to the rock so he would cut the string in
half. Yes, that's what it said, he cut it. Look, maybe he'd
bring the string back and say, 'Look, you know, it turned white!'
at least afterwards everybody would be happy. And if it didn't turn
white he would say, 'I lost it.' Right? So we have a
verse from נביא Navi being used to justify a biblical מלאכה melacha
being done on יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. I don't know if it's
a מלאכה, melacha, why is it a מלאכה? melacha? It's on the
head of a goat. Tear? Oh, yeah, he was talking about that.
If it's a string, tearing קורע koreia is a מלאכה melacha by
like a fabric. If it's something that's hard, then there's a question
exactly which category you put something in, it would be מחתך, mechatech,
and מחתך mechatech is only a problem if it's like at an
exact size. So this would not be to an exact size, so
could be that it's not actually. But you know also the goat
is carrying on its body, so it's a type of מחמר mechamer
using an animal to do מלאכה. melacha. It's, you're right, it's not
at all פשוט pashut where they got where this whole thing came
from. That's a funny thing because the fabric is the string. No,
but a fabric is multiple... the string itself is not woven. No,
right. Okay. Anyway, אמר רב נחמן בר פפא משום רבי אלעזר הקפר:
amar rav nachman bar pappa mishum rabbi eliezer hakappar: בראשונה היו קושרים
לשון של זהורית על פתח האולם מבפנים. berishonah hayu koshrim lashon shel
zehorit al petach ha'ulam mibifnim. So he says the same thing, originally
they did it on the doorway of the אולם ulam on the
inside. No, so here he's not saying originally on the outside, maybe
he's talking about... maybe they're agreeing, he's just talking about this middle
stage period. Okay, maybe he says it was never on the outside,
it was always on the inside. But that's point number one: originally
it was on the inside of the doorway. וכיון שהגיע שעיר למדבר
היה מלבין. vekeivan shehigia sair lamidbar hayah malbin. So now remember we
talked about it turning white when it was near the cliff, off
the cliff. Here it says as soon as it got to the
wilderness. וידעו שנעשית מצוותו, veyadu shena'asit mitzvato, and they would know the
מצוה mitzvah was done, not they would know they were atoned for,
they knew the מצוה mitzvah was done, שנאמר אם יהיו חטאיכם כשנים
כשלג ילבינו. shenemar im yihyu chataeichem kashanim kasheleg yalbinu. And that goes
to the point I was saying before. When is the מצוה mitzvah
done and does it correspond with when the... when it's effective and
the achievement of atonement? There was the discussion in the משנה Mishnah
when did the garments become טמא, tamei, which presumably is when... related
to the issue of when the מצוה mitzvah was done. And the
תנא קמא Tanna Kamma said the walls of ירושלים, Yerushalayim, and רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon said when it goes over the cliff. So here,
if the consensus or the standard opinion was the walls of ירושלים,
Yerushalayim, it's consistent with what we're saying here, that when it left
the walls of ירושלים Yerushalayim the מצוה mitzvah was done and that's
when it turned white. So that actually and, you know, even so
that the... it basically was done as soon as it left ירושלים,
Yerushalayim, the going over the cliff that was just finishing it up,
but it basically was done then. Maybe that's when the garments became
טמא, tamei, that's when the thing turned white. But I still want
to point out, even saying that does not mean that בדיעבד bedieved
that was necessary. We said before that בדיעבד bedieved at most what
was necessary was doing the וידוי, viduy, הגרלה והוידוי. hagralah vehaviduy. So
you could say, you know, yes בדיעבד bedieved you actually are יוצא
yotzei much earlier, but even the next stage of saying you did
the מצוה mitzvah in the ideal way, you know, even that is
just getting out of ירושלים, Yerushalayim, and then going over the cliff
is just what? Wrapping it up or something. So it's quite fascinating
these stages, we all focus on that last stage of going over
the cliff. Right, is it clear what I'm talking... what I'm saying
here? There are like three stages, right? Here you are doing the
drawing the lot, לעזאזל, la'azazel, right? And then doing the וידוי, viduy,
right? Whatever, here you are standing doing the וידוי viduy on it.
Okay. At this stage if it were to drop dead, you'd have
been יוצא. yotzei. You would have done the עבודה. avoda. Maybe would
not, I don't know, would it have achieved כפרה? kapparah? I don't
know. But would you have done the עבודה avoda of יום כיפור?
Yom Kippur? Yes. Then you go outside of ירושלים, Yerushalayim, right? This
is ירושלים. Yerushalayim. You leave ירושלים Yerushalayim and then we're saying נעשה
מצותו. na'aseh mitzvato. So which is a stage beyond יוצא. yotzei. At
this stage you're יוצא, yotzei, okay, בדיעבד bedi'avad you've done at least
the עבודה. avoda. Here the מצוה mitzvah of the שעיר sa'ir was
fully done, meaning this is the question of when does it prevent
you from fulfilling the whole עבודה avoda of יום כיפור. Yom Kippur.
If something happens earlier here, you gotta start the whole עבודה avoda
yet. But that doesn't mean you're done with the שעיר. sa'ir. Leaving
ירושלים, Yerushalayim, you've done the מצוה mitzvah of the שעיר, sa'ir, the
string becomes white, the garments become טמא, tamei, and going over the
cliff, you know, that's like just wrapping things up. So there really
are three stages: what's needed to be יוצא yotzei the whole עבודה
avoda of יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, when the עבודה avoda of the
שעיר sa'ir is considered to be done, and then actually going over
the cliff is actually a third stage. Yes. And as for the
פסוקים, pesukim, because all the פסוקים pesukim say is that ושלח ביד
איש עתי המדברה ונשא השעיר עליו את כל עונתם אל ארץ גזרה.
v'shillach b'yad ish itti hamidbarah v'nasa hasa'ir alav et kol avonotam el
eretz gezeirah. So המדברה. hamidbarah. So right, so Michael is correct in
saying that and we're going to look at that in a minute,
which is saying when you leave ירושלים Yerushalayim you're יוצא yotzei is
not a big חידוש chiddush because the whole idea of going over
a cliff, forget the red string, the whole idea of going over
a cliff isn't in the פסוקים. pesukim. Right, well so we will
see. So that actually, so that really explains why the assumption here
again that the בגדים begadim become טמא, tamei, you've done the מצוה,
mitzvah, it would turn white, all those things could happen as soon
as it left, that being seen as the primary מצוה. mitzvah. לא
היו מגיעים לחצי שעיר ההר, lo hayu magi'im lachatzi sa'ir hahar, we're
not get to halfway down the mountain before it would shatter. איבעיא
להו, iba'ya lehu, they asked the question: אותן איברים מה הן בהנאה?
otan evarim mah hen bahana'ah? After it shattered, what would be the
story, could you derive benefit from those limbs? Because it basically is
something that was sanctified, and we say that נעשית מצותו, na'asit mitzvato,
the מצוה mitzvah was done with it. So maybe there's no longer,
you could derive benefit. We had also said שחיטתו זו היא שחיטתו,
shchitato zo hi shchitato, so then I don't know if you could
eat them. Yeah, that literal no. Okay, רב ושמואל, Rav u'Shmuel, חד
אמר מותרין, chad amar mutarin, one says they are permitted, וחד אמר
אסורין, v'chad amar asurin, one says they are forbidden. מן דאמר מותרין,
man d'amar mutarin, the one who says they are permitted, דכתיב d'chtiv
במדבר bamidbar is a wilderness. So the same way מדבר midbar has
a sense of like open to anybody, no restrictions, whatever, so here
too, it's free of any restrictions. ומן דאמר אסורין, u'man d'amar asurin,
the one who says it's forbidden, דכתיב d'chtiv גזרה, gezeirah, the land
of גזרה, gezeirah, the hard land, the land of or sometimes it's
cutting, it's a sense of limit, restrictions. מן דאמר אסורין, man d'amar
asurin, the one who says it's forbidden, האי מדבר מאי עביד ליה?
hai midbar mai avid lei? If you say it's forbidden, what do
you do with the sense of במדבר? bamidbar? Oh, why you can't
just say it means literally send it into the wilderness? מיבעי ליה
לכדתניא, mibayei lei l'chid'tanya, like we learned in a ברייתא: braita: המדברה
המדברה במדבר. hamidbarah hamidbarah bamidbar. So maybe part of the issue is
it says so many times wilderness. Why does it have to say
it so many times in the פסוקים? pesukim? ושלח את השעיר המדברה
המדברה, v'shillach et hasa'ir hamidbarah hamidbarah, ושלח אותו המדברה, v'shillach oto hamidbarah,
it says multiple times send it into the wilderness. לרבות נוב וגבעון
שילה בית עולמים, l'rabot Nov u'Giv'on Shilo Beit Olamim, that not only
do you do it when you're in the משכן, Mishkan, you do
it wherever the משכן Mishkan moved and when it becomes the permanent
temple. So whether you had the משכן Mishkan in נוב וגבעון, Nov
u'Giv'on, whether you had it in שילה, Shilo, and whether finally when
it was established on הר הבית. Har HaBayit. So the repetition says
you do this ritual in all of those places. Again, fascinating why
you need a specific way of including it here, how about the
rest
of the עבודה avoda of יום כיפור? Yom Kippur?
Where's the פסוקים pesukim to tell me you do those?
We did have a discussion before, if you remember, by some aspects
of the יום כיפור Yom Kippur to
tell me it applies also
in the, also in the מקדש, Mikdash, also in the other locations.
Okay, but once interesting whether maybe this would be seen as somewhat
different, particularly because they're not here traveling in the wilderness. They are
in a settled land. So if you're in a settled land, the
same significance of sending something to the wilderness might be different. One
minute, one minute. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says, ואידך האי גזרה
מאי עביד ליה? v'idach hai gezeirah mai avid lei? If you say
it's permissible, what do you do with the language גזרה, gezeirah, which
suggests restrictions? מיבעי ליה לכדתניא, mibayei lei l'chid'tanya, to teach me what
we learned in a ברייתא: braita: גזרה אין גזרה אלא חתוכה, gezeirah
ein gezeirah ella chatucha, גזרה gezeirah means cut, לגזור, ligzor, that is
literally what it means. Which means that it has to be like
a sheer cliff, like the cliff is cut, not like an angled
slope, a sheer cliff. And that's by the way is where we
get the idea of pushing it off a cliff, from this word
גזרה. gezeirah. Again, it's not the פשט pshat of the פסוק, pasuk,
yeah, right, but it's read as push it off. Let's keep on
reading. דבר אחר אין גזרה אלא דבר המתגזר, davar acher ein gezeirah
ella davar hamitgazer, something that gets chopped up, ויורד v'yored and goes
down. So when it's pushed off the cliff it gets broken into
pieces. דבר אחר גזרה שמא תאמר מעשה תהו הוא, davar acher gezeirah
shema tomar ma'aseh tohu hu, this is quite fascinating: you'll say this
is all foolish, sending something to the עזאזל, Azazel, sending something over
a cliff? What type of service of God is this? What's the
meaning of this? You'll say it's all foolishness. אני השם. Ani Hashem.
It says I am God, right? אני השם גזרתי ואין לך רשות
להרהר בהן. Ani Hashem gezarti v'ein lach reshut le-harher bahen. I השם
Hashem have decreed this, you cannot, you have no reason, you have
no permission חוקותי תשמורו. Chukotai tishmoru. Okay, that it's אני השם. Ani
Hashem. So this is not, it's a different פסוק, pasuk, not from
this. Okay, but it's a general פסוק. pasuk. We're going to make
the דרשה derasha that sometimes we have edicts, we have מצוות mitzvot
that cannot be explained so rationally, called חוק, chok, right? And so,
and so this shows your obedience to me, even if it doesn't
make sense, you do it anyway. And that's part of hinted in
the word גזרה. gezeirah. It's a גזרה, gezeirah, גזרה, gezeirah, you do
it, I don't care, it doesn't make sense. You think it's crazy,
עזאזל, Azazel, the cliff, whatever, this is what you do. But halachically,
besides that sort of religious point, halachically what we learn from גזרה
gezeirah is this point that the פסוקים pesukim only talk about sending
it to the מדבר. midbar. We've just said that, according to some
opinions, you're יוצא yotzei the מצוה mitzvah once it goes into the
מדבר, midbar, but from גזרה gezeirah we learn the idea of sending
it over some craggy cliff. Yes, Charlie. Back to the opinion that
they were prohibited, there are three, they mentioned three locations, there were
actually four locations because משכן Mishkan was in גלגל Gilgal for a
few years after we entered the land. Presumably that was in the
Jordan Valley and therefore there wasn't a cliff to do this. I
don't know, that's a good insight. I don't know, it's a good
question. Maybe you're right, maybe that's why it wasn't mentioned, although you
could, I guess, invent one. But that also implies that השם Hashem
knew that the משכן שילה Mishkan Shilo was going to get destroyed.
All right, moving on, let's go on. אמר רבא, Amar Rava, said
רבא, Rava, מסתבר כמאן דאמר מותרים. mistabra k'man d'amar mutarim. It makes
sense the opinion that says it's permissible, the limbs. לא אמרה תורה
שלח לתקלה. Lo amra Torah shelach letakala. The תורה Torah does not
say send it into the wilderness if it'll lead to stumbling. If
it remains forbidden, you know, you have dead animal parts there, somebody's
going to come along and take it not realize, again, I don't
know why they wouldn't realize, presumably it was always the same cliff,
but anyway, you know, but therefore if it's lying there, presumably it
has to be okay, you don't want people to misuse it. That
phrase is more used by sending away the bird, you know, by
the ritual of the מצורע, metzora, because there, you send away the
bird, is that bird אסור בהנאה? assur behana'ah? Let's say the bird,
you know, a year later flies into my yard, how am I
going to know? No, the תורה Torah would never say send it
away that it would lead to stumbling. So there it makes a
little more sense because you would not know. But anyway, that's his
position here as well. תנו רבנן, Tanu rabanan, עזאזל, Azazel, what does
עזאזל Azazel mean? And again, this we're going to learn from these
words some of this idea of the cliff. שיהא עז, She-yehei az,
it should be strong, וקשה, ve-kasheh, and hard. So again, this idea
of going over like a hard cliff. יכול ביישוב? Yachol be-yishuv? Maybe
you do it, you know, in settled territory? תלמוד לומר במדבר. Talmud
lomar ba-midbar. That's quite clear in the פסוק. pasuk. It's in the
wilderness, in unsettled territory. ומניין שבצוק? U-minayin she-be-tzok? צוק, Tzok, right? צוק,
Tzok, צוק. Tzok. How do you know that צוק, tzok, how do
you know you do it over a cliff, not just a hard
land, but an actual cliff? תלמוד לומר גזרה, Talmud lomar gezeirah, which
as we said meant like a cut, so something cut down, the
sheer of a cliff. תניא אידך, Tanya idach, we learn another ברייתא.
braita. עזאזל, Azazel, קשה שבהרים. kasheh she-be-harim. It has to be a
hard mountain. Okay, the word אל el means hard. וכן הוא אומר
ואת אילי הארץ לקח, Ve-chen hu omer ve-et eilei ha-aretz lakach, the
strong ones of the land he took. So אל, el, so from
the word אל el means like it has to be, you know,
hard and strong. תנא דבי רבי ישמעאל, Tana d'vei Rabbi Yishmael, עזאזל,
Azazel, what does that mean? שמכפר על מעשה עוזא ועזאל. She-mechaper al
ma'aseh Uza ve-Aza'el. It atones for the sin of עוזא Uza and
עזאל. Aza'el. Who are עוזא Uza and עזאל? Aza'el? So if you
look at רש"י, Rashi, רש"י Rashi says about ten lines down in
the narrow lines, מלאכי חבלה, malachei chavala, angels of destruction, שירדו לארץ
בימי נעמה אחות תובל קין, she-yardu la-aretz bimei Na'amah achot Tuval Kayin,
that went down to the land in the days of נעמה Na'amah
the sister of תובל קין, Tuval Kayin, דעליהם נאמר ויראו בני האלוהים
את בנות האדם. de-aleihem ne'emar va-yir'u bnei ha-elohim et bnot ha-adam. These
were the angels of destruction who were taking the human women and
raping them. כלומר על עריות מכפר. Klomar al arayot mechaper. So רש"י
Rashi says, oh, what it means is it atones for the sin
of sexual sins. Of course, I didn't think he was going there.
It's almost like it's quoting this type of the whole idea of
עזאזל Azazel seems very mythic and quoting this mythic story, you know,
about בני אלוהים, bnei elohim, maybe you're thinking it's something being played
out at that sort of mythic plane like some type of drama.
But רש"י Rashi brings it back down to earth to talk about
עריות. arayot. תנו רבנן, Tanu rabanan, yes, תנו רבנן, Tanu rabanan, את
משפטי תעשו. et mishpatai ta'asu. This is what we referred to before.
Okay, this is a פסוק pasuk from that area in קדושים Kedoshim
and right there in אחרי מות. Acharei Mot. Okay, do my edicts.
So what are משפטים, mishpatim, laws? So those are rational laws. דברים
שאלמלא נכתבו דין הוא שיכתבו. Devarim she-ilmalei nichtevu din hu she-yichtevu. These
are things that even if they had not been written, it would
have made sense for them to have been written. These are rational
laws you could have, that anybody would have, would have had in
a legal system. For example... עבודת כוכבים, avodat kochavim, idolatry—well, that’s a
rational law in a religious system that believes in one God—גילוי עריות,
gilui arayot, sexual sins, and sexual prohibitions, ושפיכות דמים ve-shefichut damim and
murder, וגזל ve-gezel and theft, וברכת השם u-virchat Hashem and cursing God.
Notice by the way that every single one of those is what?
שבע מצוות בני נח. sheva mitzvot bnei Noach. They're the מצוות שכליות.
mitzvot sichliyot. So this by the way is important because, yes, מצוות
שכליות mitzvot sichliyot is how it's talked about by the medieval philosophers.
But it's important because according to some philosophers, particularly Mendelssohn, wants to
see in the שבע מצוות בני נח sheva mitzvot bnei Noach a
type of natural law, not something that needed to be revealed. But
רמב"ם Rambam disagrees. רמב"ם Rambam emphasized that somebody only has the status
of observing שבע מצוות בני נח, sheva mitzvot bnei Noach, a non-Jew,
it only gives him his particular unique special status if he does
it because he believes in it as revealed law. Okay, but you
know, Mendelssohn was very upset about that רמב"ם. Rambam. So anyway, but
here the גמרא Gemara really is taking the ones it lists explicitly
are almost all of the שבע מצוות sheva mitzvot and lists them
as things that would have been, you could have figured out by
yourself. This seems to be more on the side of Mendelssohn. Right.
Well, that was my point. On the side, by the way, you'll
see that it refers to a רמב"ם Rambam in שמונה פרקים Shmona
Perakim that does not include גילוי עריות gilui arayot in the משפטים,
mishpatim, included in the חוקים. chukim. And that's an interesting question. What
type of גילוי עריות? gilui arayot? Are we talking about adultery? Are
we talking about incest? Are we talking about נדה? niddah? So, you
know, which one you're talking about might also determine whether you put
it in the rational laws or in the more in the חוקים,
chukim, the more edicts and arbitrary laws. One minute. Okay. את חוקותי
תשמרו. et chukotai tishmoru. Now, my חוקות, chukot, my edicts, that's not
the rational laws. That's דברים שהשטן משיב עליהם. devarim she-ha-Satan meishiv aleihem.
Those are things that the Satan would, you know, or יצר הרע
yeitzer ha-ra would basically have what to respond, would critique them and
say, what, these are nonsense, or these are arbitrary, they don't make
any, you know, they're not rational. ואלו הן, ve-elu hein, these are
they: אכילת חזיר, achilat chazir, forbidden foods, pork, ולבישת שעטנז, ve-levishat shatnez,
wearing שעטנז, shatnez, what's the big deal, you know, things woven together.
וחליצת יבמה, ve-chalitzat yevamah, and doing the חליצה chalitzah for a יבמה.
yevamah. And it doesn't say the יבום yibbum for a יבמה, yevamah,
right? Because anyway, so if you look at the פסוקים, psukim, right,
you get by the whole thing, Yehuda and Tamar, sounds like that
was actually something going on in the ancient world. Maybe it's freeing
you from it, and doing the חליצה, chalitzah, why the act of
חליצה chalitzah is what is significant. וטהרת מצורע, ve-taharat metzora, the purification
of the מצורע, metzora, the whole thing with the birds, right, seems
very hocus pocusy. ושעיר המשתלח, ve-sa'ir ha-mishtaleach, again, קרבנות korbanot we get.
Ancient world, קרבנות korbanot is certainly a meaningful religious practice, but what
is this עזאזל Azazel over a cliff? ושמא תאמר מעשה תהו הם,
ve-shemma tomar ma'aseh tohu heim, lest you say this is all foolishness.
תלמוד לומר, talmud lomar, אני השם, Ani Hashem, I am God. אני
חקקתיו ואין לך רשות להרהר בהן. Ani chakaktiv ve-ein lecha reshut le-harheir
ba-hen. This is משפטי תעשו וחוקותי תשמרו, mishpatai ta'asu ve-chukotai tishmoru, אני
השם. Ani Hashem. I'm the one that made this חוק chok and
therefore show your obedience. This is not something that I'm going to
justify to you. By the way, רמב"ם Rambam does have a very
important difference between the issues of חוק chok and משפטים mishpatim because
he's dealing with the famous גמרא Gemara that says it is better
to say, "Don't say I don't want to sin, say I want
to sin but what should I do? God has told me not
to." But he says, but that's against what the philosophers say. The
philosophers say it's better to internalize an ethic rather than to do
it external, meaning you should better say "I don't want to steal,
I don't want to murder." That's actually a higher ethical plane than
saying "I want to steal but I'm not going to do it
because the law's against it." So the רמב"ם Rambam has his way
to, to מיישב meyashev the philosophers and the rabbis. And he says
it depends, are we talking about rational laws or are we talking
about these חוקים? chukim? The rational laws are things that reflect values
and character traits that you're supposed to internalize. The חוקים chukim underscore
obedience. So those, if you want to eat חזיר chazir and you
don't do it because God says so, that's actually the ideal because
those actually underscore obedience. Just going to finish the משנה. Mishnah. אימתי
מטמא בגדים? eimatai metamei vegadim? When does it cause the garments to
become טמא? tamei? תנו רבנן: tanu rabbanan: המשלח מטמא בגדים ואין השולח
את המשלח מטמא בגדים. ha-meshaleach metamei vegadim ve-ein ha-sholeiach et ha-meshaleach metamei
vegadim. The guy with the goat gets טמא, tamei, but not the
people that are accompanying him, right, the people that went from סוכה
sukkah to סוכה. sukkah. I don't know, because they're associated. יכול משיצא
חוץ לחומת העזרה? yachol mi-she-yatza chutz le-chomat ha-azarah? Maybe from the time
you left the temple courtyard? תלמוד לומר: talmud lomar: המשלח, ha-meshaleach, the
one who sends it, so you have to already be sending it
into the wilderness, you have to be in the wilderness. יהיה משלח
יכול עד שיגיע לצוק? yihiyeh meshaleach yachol ad she-yagiya la-tzuk? Anyway, until
you get to the cliff? תלמוד לומר: talmud lomar: והמשלח, ve-ha-meshaleach, somehow
and the one that sends means when you begin the process of
sending once you get to the wilderness. הכיצד? ha-keitzad? How does this
work? משיצא חוץ לחומת ירושלים. mi-she-yatza chutz le-chomat Yerushalayim. As long as
you leave ירושלים, Yerushalayim, you've already gotten it out and you're towards
the wilderness. דברי רבי יהודה. divrei Rabbi Yehuda. רבי יוסי אומר: Rabbi
Yossi omer: עזאזל וכבס. Azazel ve-chibbes. He juxtaposes the word, the hard
land, and you clean your clothes. עד שיהיה לצוק. ad she-yihiyeh la-tzuk.
And עזאזל Azazel we learn associates it with the cliff, so it
only becomes טמא. tamei. When you get to the cliff. רבי שמעון
אומר, Rabbi Shimon omer, והמשלח את השעיר לעזאזל יכבס בגדיו. ve-hameshaleach et
ha-sa'ir la-Azazel yechabes begadav. So the one who sent has to cleanse
clothes. זורקו בבת אחת zorko be-vat achat ומטמא בגדים. umetameh begadim. So
he says you actually it's not just getting to the cliff, you
push it over and then it becomes טמא, tameh, only when it
actually goes over the... what? I don't know. זורקו, zorko, I don't
know, somehow you push it over and then it's only there, it's
not just getting to the cliff. Okay. And then we spelled...